<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: linuxfest | system templar]]></title>
  <link href="http://shawn-sterling.github.com/blog/categories/linuxfest/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://shawn-sterling.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-25T22:50:03-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://shawn-sterling.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[shawn sterling]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Linuxfest 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://shawn-sterling.github.com/blog/2013/05/04/linuxfest-2013/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-04T13:02:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://shawn-sterling.github.com/blog/2013/05/04/linuxfest-2013</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Linuxfest Northwest 2013</h3>

<p>I went to <a href="http://linuxfestnorthwest.org/">Linuxfest Northwest</a> again this
year, and I had a great time.</p>

<p>This year I organized the <a href="http://linuxfestnorthwest.org/content/lightning-talks">Lightning Talks</a>
 and plan on doing the lightning talks each year at linuxfest. We had a great
variety of lightning talks, it was pretty fun.</p>

<p>I also did a session called "I wanna be the guy - The arduous path to senior
sysadmin or How to be a better system administrator" which you can see here:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/bSAgQqa49nM "></iframe></div></p>

<p>It is my first talk at a conference but I hope to do more in the future.</p>

<p>It took a while to get online, as I first did the video with
<a href="http://www.openshotvideo.com/">openshot</a> but what was on the video preview was
not what the end video looked like. So I tried to work around it with openshot
but eventually gave up. Did the same thing uses a friend's copy of
<a href="http://www.sonycreativesoftware.com/vegassoftware">Vegas</a> and it was a much
nicer experience. Openshot is <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/421164014/openshot-video-editor-for-windows-mac-and-linux">working on a new
UI</a>
 and I look forward to using it the next time I need to cut some video together.</p>

<h3>The fest</h3>

<p>Linuxfest Northwest 2013 was very fun, I like the sessions and meeting fellow
linux enthusiasts. I'm more interested in finding other system administrators
so I am always on the hunt to find them. Maybe I need to do an early birds of a
feather for sysadmins so I can find out who the sysadmins are nice and early
and then try to find them through-out the day.</p>

<p>The ID badge for lfnw deserves special mention. I have been to several
conferences but this was the first that I have been to that had this type of
badge. The badge was essentially a small booklet, on the front and back was
your name and information; but inside the booklet was the conference schedule,
and maps to the various rooms and events going on. This was very cool.</p>

<p>The after party on Saturday was at a museum called <a href="http://www.whatcommuseum.org/about/buildings">The
lightcatcher</a>. There were several nice exhibits, I liked the
glass sculptures; but I didn't think to take any pictures
(which may have not been allowed, I don't remember). I didn't stay very late at
the after party because I needed to finish up my slides (for the talk i was
giving the next day).</p>

<p>I look forward to linuxfest 2014.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
